There is a beautiful explanation from the אלטר
מקלם Alter mi-Kelm on the words אעשה לו עזר
כנגדו. E’eseh lo ezer k’negdo. We know the famous רש״י Rashi that
says זכה עזר לא זכה כנגדו. zachah ezer, lo zachah k’negdo. If
a man is worthy, his wife is
a helper, but if he is not
worthy, she is against him. The אלטר
Alter explains that being כנגדו, k’negdo, being against
him, is actually a type of עזר,
ezer, a type of help. If a
person is heading in the wrong direction,
if he is about to fall into
a pit, then the greatest עזר, ezer, the
greatest help someone can provide, is to
stand כנגדו, k’negdo, to stand in his way
and stop him from making a mistake.
This is the goal of a spouse,
to help the other person grow, and
sometimes that help comes in the form
of opposition. And this is a very
powerful lesson because sometimes we think that
a leader is somebody who has a
vision and everybody has to follow that
vision. But the true Jewish definition of
a leader is somebody who's able to
relate to each person individually according to
their unique temperament, according to their unique
soul. And we see this in the
fact that it is immediately after the
request of משה Moshe that השם Hashem would appoint
a leader for the Jewish people that
the תורה Torah teaches us the laws of
inheritance. Why are the laws of inheritance
connected to the appointment of a new
leader? It's because just like an inheritance
is something which is passed down from
parents to children, so too leadership is
something which must be passed down. The
leader must be somebody who's able to
recognize the unique qualities of each and
every person, just as a parent recognizes
the unique qualities of each and every
one of their children. And it is
specifically in this context that we find
the story of the בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzelofchad, the
daughters of צלפחד, Tzelofchad, who come to משה
Moshe and say that our father has
passed away without a son and we
would like to inherit his portion in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And משה Moshe goes to השם
Hashem and השם Hashem says כן בנות צלפחד
דברת, Ken Bnot Tzelofchad dovrot, the daughters of צלפחד Tzelofchad are correct,
they should receive their father's portion. This
shows that the leader of the Jewish
people must be somebody who's willing to
listen even to those who may seem
to have a smaller voice in the
community and to recognize the justice of
their claims. And then השם Hashem tells משה
Moshe to appoint יהושע בן נון Yehoshua Bin Nun as
his successor. Why יהושע? Yehoshua? Because he was
the one who was constantly with משה,
Moshe, he was the one who served
משה Moshe and he was the one who
understood the unique qualities of the Jewish
people. יהושע Yehoshua is described as an איש
אשר רוח בו, Ish asher ruach bo, a man in whom
is spirit. And רש״י Rashi explains that this
means that he was able to relate
to the spirit of each and every
individual. This is the essence of Jewish
leadership, the ability to recognize the individuality
of each person while still leading the
entire community forward towards a common goal.
May we all merit to have leaders
who are able to relate to us
in this way and may we also
strive to be leaders in our own
lives, recognizing the unique qualities of those
around us and treating them with the
respect and the dignity that they deserve.
שבת שלום. Shabbat Shalom. So we have to see
the נודע ביהודה Noda BiYehuda in the נודע ביהודה
תניינא, Noda BiYehuda Tinyana, אורח חיים, Orach Chaim, סימן י"ג. Siman Yud
Gimmel. There he talks about the city
of צפת. Tzfat. He was asked whether they
can make an עירוב eruv in the city
of צפת. Tzfat. Now, the city of צפת
Tzfat is on a mountain and the
streets are very steep. And the question
was whether the steepness of the streets
would prevent it from being a רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. Because for a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, you
need it to be מפולש. mefulash. It has
to be a straight throughway. And the
נודע ביהודה Noda BiYehuda says that since it's on
a mountain and it's so steep, it's
not considered מפולש. mefulash. And if it's not
מפולש, mefulash, it's not a רשות הרבים דאורייתא.
reshus harabbim d'Oraisa. And therefore, even without
the requirement of ששים ריבוא, shishim ribo, it's still
not a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. It's a כרמלית.
karmelis. And therefore they could make an
עירוב. eruv. This is a very important תשובה
teshuva for the laws of שבת. Shabbos. Six.
הנני. Hineni. The prayer beginning with the word
הנני Hineni is a special תפילה Tefilla recited by
the חזן Chazan before the מוסף Musaf עמידה Amida of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. In this
תפילה, Tefilla, the חזן Chazan expresses his humility and
unworthiness as he prepares to lead the
congregation in the מוסף Musaf service. While the
חזן Chazan is reciting הנני, Hineni, the congregation should
listen attentively and answer אמן Amen at the
end. One who has not yet finished
his silent עמידה Amida when the חזן Chazan begins
הנני Hineni should finish his עמידה Amida and then
listen to the remainder of הנני. Hineni. If
he has already finished his עמידה, Amida, he
may join the חזן Chazan in reciting הנני
Hineni in an undertone. Seven. נשיאת כפים.
Nesi'as Kapayim. On ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, the כהנים
Kohanim perform נשיאת כפים Nesi'as Kapayim during the חזרת
הש"ץ Chazaras Hashatz of the מוסף Musaf עמידה. Amida. In accordance
with widespread custom, the כהנים Kohanim do not
perform נשיאת כפים Nesi'as Kapayim during שחרית. Shacharis. Before starting
the מוסף Musaf עמידה, Amida, the כהנים Kohanim must wash
their hands. A לוי Levi should pour the
water over their hands. If there is
no לוי Levi present, the כהנים Kohanim should wash
their own hands. After washing, the כהנים
Kohanim should stand at the front of
the בית כנסת Beis Knesses near the ארון קודש.
Aron Kodesh. When the חזן Chazan reaches the
ברכה Beracha of מודים, Modim, the כהנים Kohanim should prepare
to perform נשיאת כפים. Nesi'as Kapayim. When the חזן
Chazan reaches the ברכה Beracha of רצה, Retzei, the
כהנים Kohanim should say the following prayer: יהי
רצון מלפניך ה' אלוהינו ואלוהי אבותינו שתהא
הברכה הזאת שציוויתנו לברך את עמך ישראל
ברכה שלמה ולא יהיה בה שום מכשול
ועוון מעתה ועד עולם. Yehi ratzon milfanecha Hashem Elokeinu v'Elokei avoseinu she'tehei
ha'beracha hazos she'tzivisanu l'varech es amcha Yisrael
beracha sheleima v'lo yehei bah shum michshol
v'avon mei'atah v'ad olam. When the חזן
Chazan reaches the words וכל החיים, V'chol ha'chayim, the
כהנים Kohanim should finish their prayer. Then the
congregation says אמן. Amen. When the חזן Chazan reaches
the words המחזיר שכינתו לציון, Ha'machazir Shechinaso l'Tziyon, the congregation
responds with אמן. Amen. Then the חזן Chazan says
אלוהינו ואלוהי אבותינו ברכנו בברכה המשולשת בתורה.
Elokeinu v'Elokei avoseinu barcheinu ba'beracha ha'meshuleshes ba'Torah.
Then the congregation should say the word
כהנים Kohanim and then the כהנים Kohanim begin the
ברכה. Beracha. They say ברוך אתה ה' אלוהינו
מלך העולם אשר קדשנו בקדושתו של אהרן
וציוונו לברך את עמו ישראל באהבה. Baruch atah Hashem Elokeinu melech ha'olam
asher kideshanu bikdushaso shel Aharon v'tzivanu l'varech
es amo Yisrael b'ahava. The congregation should
answer אמן Amen at the end of the
ברכה. Beracha. Then the כהנים Kohanim recite the three
פסוקים Pesukim of ברכת כהנים. Birkas Kohanim. The חזן Chazan prompts
them word by word. After each word
recited by the כהנים, Kohanim, the congregation should
not answer אמן. Amen. Rather, they should listen
and respond אמן Amen only at the end
of each of the three פסוקים. Pesukim. After
each פסוק, Pasuk, the congregation should say a
special תפילה. Tefilla. After יברכך, Yevarechecha, they say יהי
רצון מלפניך ה' אלוהינו ואלוהי אבותינו שבזכות
ברכה זו Yehi ratzon milfanecha Hashem Elokeinu v'Elokei avoseinu she'bizchus beracha zu
and so on for each of the
three פסוקים. Pesukim. These prayers are found in
the מחזור. Machzor. While the כהנים Kohanim are performing
נשיאת כפים, Nesi'as Kapayim, they should stand with their
faces toward the congregation. The members of
the congregation should stand and face the
כהנים. Kohanim. It is forbidden for anyone to
look at the כהנים Kohanim while they are
performing נשיאת כפים. Nesi'as Kapayim. This is because the
שכינה Shechina rests upon the כהנים Kohanim at that
time. Even the כהנים Kohanim should not look
at their own hands. They should look
down at the floor or close their
eyes. Members of the congregation should also
look down at the floor or close
their eyes or look into their מחזורים.
Machzorim. Eight. עלינו. Aleinu. During the חזרת הש"ץ
Chazaras Hashatz of the מוסף Musaf עמידה, Amida, when
the חזן Chazan reaches the words ואנחנו כורעים
ומשתחווים ומודים Va'anachnu korim u'mishtachavim u'modim in the תפילה Tefilla of עלינו,
Aleinu, it is the custom for the
entire congregation and the חזן Chazan to prostrate
themselves on the floor. Before prostrating himself,
one should spread a piece of cloth
or paper on the floor to separate
between his face and the floor. This
is because it is forbidden to prostrate
oneself on a stone floor. Nine. The
sounding of the שופר Shofar during the חזרת
הש"ץ. Chazaras Hashatz. According to the custom of most
communities, the שופר Shofar is sounded during the
חזרת הש"ץ Chazaras Hashatz of the מוסף Musaf עמידה. Amida. Thirty
sounds are blown. Ten after the ברכה
Beracha of מלכויות, Malchuyos, ten after the ברכה
Beracha of זכרונות, Zichronos, and ten after the
ברכה Beracha of שופרות. Shofros. Some communities have the
custom of sounding the שופר Shofar also during
the silent מוסף Musaf עמידה. Amida. Ten. הקפות. Hakafos. In
some communities, it is the custom to
perform הקפות Hakafos with the ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah on
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. This is usually done after
the מוסף Musaf service. The congregation marches around
the בימה Bima while special פיוטים Piyutim are recited.
Eleven. שיר של יום. Shir shel Yom. After the מוסף
Musaf service, the שיר של יום Shir shel Yom is
recited followed by אדון עולם. Adon Olam. אמר אביי.
Amar Abaye. Abaye says as follows. עושה
אדם צורת הפתח oseh adam tzuras hapesach even if there are
no דפנות. dofnos. So Abaye is saying you
can build your סוכה Sukkah walls using the
צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach which as we know is
two side posts and a crossbeam on
top and that is considered a valid
מחיצה. mechitza. This is the הלכה halacha that we
know from the laws of שבת Shabbos in
מסכת עירובין Masechet Eruvin and Abaye is saying it
is מועיל mo'il here too in סוכה. Sukkah. Now
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask wait
we have a ברייתא braisa that says you
need שתיים כהלכתן ושלישית אפילו טפח. shtayim kehilchatan v'shlishit afilu tefach. You
need two real walls and the third one can be just a
small piece like a טפח. tefach. It doesn't mention צורת הפתח. tzuras
hapesach. So how can Abaye say that a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach
is enough? The גמרא Gemara will have to reconcile Abaye's statement with
the ברייתא. braisa. And we're going to look into what the ראשונים
Rishonim say about this like רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot to understand
the exact scope of this הלכה. halacha. In our daily life, we
often find ourselves facing many different challenges. The תורה Torah provides us
with a roadmap of how to navigate through these difficult times. When
we look at the פרשה, Parsha, we see that the אבות Avos
and אמהות Imahos all went through their own personal struggles. Yet, they
remained strong in their אמונה Emunah in the הקדוש ברוך הוא. HaKadosh
Baruch Hu. We have a rule in the גמרא Gemara that מעשה
אבות סימן לבנים, Ma'aseh Avos Siman Labanim, which means that the actions
of the fathers are a sign for the children. By learning from
their lives, we can find the strength to overcome our own obstacles.
This is the beauty of learning תורה Torah and living a life
of מצוות. Mitzvos. So let's try to put our heart and soul
into our דאוון davening and really connect with our Father in Heaven.
We should also remember that the words of the תפילה tefillah were
composed by the אנשי כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Knesset Hagedolah. They were giants
in רוחניות ruchaniut and knew exactly what each word represents. When we
say the words, we are tapping into a higher source. Each ברכה
berakhah has its own significance. For example, in the first ברכה, berakhah,
we mention the אבות, Avos, אברהם, יצחק, ויעקב. Avraham, Yitzchak, v'Yaakov. We
ask השם Hashem to remember their merit. In the זכות zechus of
our ancestors, may our prayers be answered. It's a beautiful way to
start the שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, connecting ourselves to our history and
our roots. So next time you stand up to דאוון, daven, take
a moment to reflect on these
ideas.
It
will
surely
elevate
your
תפילה tefillah
to
a
whole
new
level.